how many times do you think that you've
been lied to today go ahead and take a
guess because the answer might shock you
studies show that on the low end that
number is somewhere around 10 times and
on the high end that number could be up
to 200 times in just one day you are
being lied to
constantly what's worse your lie
detection capabilities are definitely
not 100% in fact studies show that they
could be anywhere from 50% wrong to 75%
wrong this video is meant to put the
odds back in your favor because there
are things that you are probably not
taught they can help you become a human
lie detector or at least a better one
and I want to cover those four things
plus touch on some examples of some
masterful Liars getting caught in the
act so let's start with the first thing
that one that everyone wants to know
which is what is the body language that
indicate slime no unfortunately there
really isn't one thing that is going to
a hundred percent of the time tell you
someone's lime when you're looking to
detect lying in terms of body language
what you're looking for are tells of
stress with regards to a particular
subject or topic and what that means is
that reading stress in the body is
actually much easier than reading
deception right stress comes through in
a lot of different ways and you can see
it in pacifying behaviors so that might
be rubbing of the arm if they're sitting
you can see people rub their leg you'll
see people start to touch right here
that's a pacifying behavior and went to
meatball - on their lip cross their arms
curse their lips I give you one of those
all of these things create lowered like
trying to calm yourself down response
and we do that in response to stress now
there's one thing that is classic when
people feel stress and it's called
blocking that means putting anything
between themselves and the thing that is
causing them stress so the classic lying
example of blocking would be this
locking the mouth could be covering the
eyes or it could be an object right and
right at the time that you're supposed
you're asking them if they're lying
they gotta whip their phone out or they
simply move something
in between you and them on the desk
blocking is very common and I want to
show you two videos of blocking the
first one is a little boy
doing some physical blocking with the
hands and the second one is a little
girl
moving herself in between an object to
create some distance between her mom who
is grilling her who get the paint out
brother did wait let me see it again you
didn't do that speak up you still didn't
do this I know you did it
Nani now I mentioned earlier that there
isn't just one body language motion that
indicates a lie but actually there is
one that comes close and it is the
microexpression
of a smile within a story that otherwise
doesn't warrant a smile this is called
duping delight and what this is first
off a microexpression is when some sort
of expression registers on someone's
face for less than a second and is
quickly contained and the reason that
this happens is that the part of your
brain that is responsible for emotions
happy sad whatever it is that moves a
fraction of a second faster than the
part of your brain that is responsible
for lying so when you tell a lie there's
actually this visceral joy in getting
away and getting what you want which
registers for second as a smile but then
the part of your brain telling the lie
kicks in it goes don't do that and
quickly shuts it down so it looks
something I'll try my best like this
finish the story and then people often
purse their lips so I want to show you a
quick example of that and that's better
than I can do which is again another
young girl master liar here who the
context of this is that she wants
attention from her mother and for months
and months and months she has pretended
to have these crippling foot cramps so
that her mom will come rub her feet and
give her attention pay attention to her
face as soon as her mom starts to touch
her feet and she gets what she wants
can you give it a rest tongue please
let's play cars
[Music]
okay if you start to see some tells of
stress maybe some duping delight on
someone's face you're going to want to
follow up with them verbally and asked
very directly hey did you do that thing
that I asked you not to do and in this
case you want to listen very carefully
to their verbal response because people
don't like to lie and the third thing
that will help you catch a liar is that
they often redirect direct questions to
some other topic or they have answer
them for instance if I go up to someone
and I say hey did you take my money they
might respond by saying oh my god I'm
not that kind of a person or how could
you even ask that of me and then pull
out their phone and immediately block
right these sorts of things are called
redirects do they immediately indicate
guilt absolutely not but what we find in
Liars is that they try to tell as much
of the truth as possible until they are
pushed to the brink
will they flat-out lie absolutely but
sometimes they'll even add qualifiers on
the end of their denials so I say hey
did you take my money they'll go no I
didn't take your money out of your
wallet when really they took money off
of the kitchen table or whatever it was
so I've got another video here the
context is that there's this young boy
who has clearly made a mess and his dad
asked him did you know who did this and
he answers a completely different
question
it seems exaggerated but the truth is
kids have the same strategies as adults
we are just better at masking them and
telling more elaborate stories you know
what happened I guess you were
stretching haha how did the Temne fall I
can put it back up how did it fall how
did it fall I believe you but what
happened so at this point let's say that
you've seen a tell maybe you've seen
that duping delight when asked they've
said how could you even ask that of me
now you're kind of put in a pickle so
when it comes down to it you can always
go at that listen I'm having a hard time
understanding what happened can you tell
me and then the fourth thing that you're
looking for is to see if this person can
recreate the events of what actually
happened out of sequential order liars
whether they're making it up on the spot
or they've rehearsed it often have done
this before and they've done
chronologically right so it can make
sense chronologically but when you ask
them so wait a second how is the money
over here at the end and then when did
you walk into the room and what happened
later when you take them out of order
you can oftentimes trip them up so of
course another little example a fun one
here which is really easy to bust cuz
he's a five year old boy here's a boy
who took cookies out of the cookie jar
and blamed it on the dog and watch as
the story unravels as different elements
don't add up
did she get the cookies upstairs
I know I wasn't locked in here how did
she open the lid tell herself baby see
often get left her teeth she opened the
lid with her teeth
yeah then she ate some cookies how did
she put the lid back on
she jumped on it she jumped on the bowl
of cookies to put the lid back on so
there you have it that is how we spot a
master liar of any age now obviously I
had some fun picking out the videos
today they entertained me and I hope
they entertain you as well but the truth
is kids and adults lie in the same way
so the same four things that I gave you
today will work across the age group
first off you're paying attention for
any sort of pacifying or blocking
behavior with regards to a specific
subject if it differs from their
baseline and all of a sudden they start
blocking or pacifying pay more attention
second duping delay that is the quick
flash and then the containment of a
smile with a story that shouldn't have a
smile on it third difficulty in outright
denying that they did something wrong
any sort of verbal jujitsu that means
you need to dig deeper and then of
course fourth you're paying attention to
see if they can reconstruct their
version of events outside of
chronological order if they think about
it here it's fine but it needs to make a
logical consistent sense so hope that
you guys have enjoyed this video and
maybe we'll start detecting some of
those 200 lies that you might be hearing
every single day if you've enjoyed this
one go ahead and make sure to subscribe
to the channel we have tons of videos on
how to boost your charisma your
confidence and of course your ability to
read social situations so if you never
want to miss one of those click
Subscribe and you'll see us on your home
page every single week hope that you've
enjoyed this video and I look forward
and to seeing you in the next one